Guide to the Donald Oenslager Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Donald Oenslager papers
1925-1974
MS 1416
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
52.5
(34 boxes)
The papers include clippings, albums, photographs, glass slides, and set designs documenting the career of Donald Oenslager as educator and set designer.
Oenslager, Donald, 1902-1975
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Glass teaching slides (14 linear ft.) were transferred 1991 Feb from Accession 86-A-26, Drama School Records, YRG 22-A. Transferred from the Drama Library, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
Set designs and sketches inthe Original accession are unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks.
All other materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged as received.
Biographical / Historical
Donald Mitchell Oenslager was born on March 7, 1902, in Harrisburg, Pennsylvania. Following graduation from Harvard University in 1923, he was an instructor in scenic design at Middlebury College, Vermont. In 1925, his former Harvard instructor, George Pierce Baker, appointed him to the faculty of the Department of Drama of the Yale School of Fine Arts. Oenslager taught design at Yale until his retirement in 1970. While at Yale, he designed sets for over 250 plays, operas, ballets, and musicals in New Haven, New York, and Europe. Oenslager served as a consultant on theater architecture and design and authored several books on the subject. He was a member of the Art Commission of the City of New York, the board of directors of the American Foundation of the Arts, and the Museum of the City of NewYork. Oenslager died on June 21, 1975, in Bedford, New York.
Scope and Contents
The papers include clippings, albums, photographs, glass slides, and set designs documenting the career of Donald Oenslager as educator and set designer.
Drama; Set designers; Oenslager, Donald, 1902-1975; Yale University -- Faculty
- Original Accession, 1941-1974
  - Topical files, A-Z, 1941 - 1974 (Box 1)
  - Photographs [negatives and slides], Undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs [productions, A-Z], Undated (Box 3)
  - Printed material, 1946 - 1972 (Box 4)
  - Glass teaching slides (Box 5–18)
  - Set designs and sketches (Box 19–22)
    Conditions Governing Access
    The materials are unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks.
- Additional material, Circa 1925-circa 1960s; Accession 2007-M-055
  Scope and Contents
  This accession consists of set designs created by Oenslager, listed alphabetically by name of production, and by his students, listed alphabetically by student name. The student designs were submitted for possible use in an exhibit of student work in honor of Oenslager in the 1970s.
  - Works by Oenslager
    - Set design renderings, may include costume designs
      - The Beautiful Galathea, Central City Opera, costumes designs for Midas and Pygmalion, 1951 (Box 5)
      - The Birds, Undated (Box 3)
      - Born Yesterday, 1946 (Box 3)
      - Candida, 1951 (Box 3)
      - Egmont, 1949 (Box 1)
      - Fantasy of France, Undated (Box 1)
      - For Country, Undated (Box 3)
      - Horses in Midstream, 1953 (Box 1)
      - Janus, 1955 (Box 3)
      - Lady From Colorado, with libretto by Bernard Stambler and score by Robert Ward, 1964 (Box 1)
      - The Leading Lady, Undated (Box 1)
      - Life with Mother, 1948 (Box 1)
      - Madam Will You Walk, Undated (Box 3)
      - Merry Widow, 1967 (Box 3)
      - Morals, Undated (Box 4)
      - My Dear Children, 1940 (Box 1)
      - Park Avenue, 1946 (Box 2)
      - Peer Gynt, Undated (Box 4)
      - Pinwheel, Undated (Box 4)
      - Portrait of a Lady, Undated (Box 2)
      - Prescott Proposals, 1953 (Box 2)
      - The Prisoner, 1960 (Box 4)
      - A Quiet Place, Undated (Box 2)
      - Second Threshold, 1951 (Box 2)
      - Sooner or Later, Undated (Box 4)
      - Three to Make Ready, 1946 (Box 2)
      - Venus at Large, Undated (Box 4)
      - Whistling in the Dark, 1932 (Box 2)
      - Yale, Undated (Box 2)
      - Years Ago, 1946 (Box 4)
    - Pencil sketches
      - The Abduction from the Seraglio, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - And Perhaps Happiness, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Antigone, American Shakespeare Festival, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Anything Goes, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - As You Like It, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - At War with the Army, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Beverly Hills, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - The Bo Tree, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Candida, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Caricoa ??, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Choose Your Partners, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Double or Nothing, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Egmont, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - The Fatal Weakness, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - The Father, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Galathea, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - The Girls in 509, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Goodbye My Fancy, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - The Highest Tree, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Horses in Midstream, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - How I Wonder, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - The Irregular Verb to Love, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - J.B., Yale University Theatre, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Janus, Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Judith Anderson's Bible series, TV, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Judith's Garden Flower Shop, Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - The Lady From Colorado, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - The Lady Who Came to Stay, Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Land's End, Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - The Leading Lady, Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - The Liars, Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Lie Down in Darkness, Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Life With Mother, Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - The Live Wire, Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Loco, Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Madam Will You Walk, Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Marco Polo, Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - The Men We Marry, Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - The Merry Widow, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - My Dear Children, Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Nature's Way, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - One by One, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Out West It's Different, Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Paris '90, Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Park Avenue, Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Peer Gynt, Undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - The Pleasure of His Company, Undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - The Poor Sailor, Undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Portrait of a Lady, Undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Present Laughter, Undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - The Prisoner, City Center, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - A Quiet Place, Undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - The Rat Race, Undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Robin Landing, Undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Sabrina Fair, Undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Second Threshold, Undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Shadow of my Enemy, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Small Hours, Undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Smile of the World, Undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Springboard to Nowhere, Undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Sweet Mystery of Life, Undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - The Temporary Mrs. Smith, Undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Three to Make Ready, Undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - To Be Continued, Undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Venus at Large, Undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Washington Square, Undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - White Haired Boy, Undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - The Wooden Dish, Undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Writer's Cramp, Undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Years Ago, Undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Miscellaneous, possibly Samoa, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Works by students of Oenslager
    - Amlund, Dale, The Simple Life, Undated (Box 7)
    - Armstrong, Will Steven, Julius Caesar, Stratford, 1966 (Box 7)
    - Baranovic, Boris
      - Die Zauberflöte, two costumes, 1966 (Box 7)
      - Dreigroschenoper, costumes for Jenny and Coaxer, 1965 (Box 7)
    - Bernard, Jules E., No Exit, Undated (Box 7)
    - Beven, The Merchant, Undated (Box 7)
    - Bianchi, Richard, The Buskers, Cricket Theater, New York, 1961 (Box 7)
    - Bohen [possibly Cohen], Michael
      - Electra, Undated (Box 7)
      - Resurrection, 1958 (Box 7)
    - Bohnert, William. T.
      - "Bracia and Tybee Dance" for Ed Sullivan Show, Undated (Box 7)
      - Jerome Robbins ballet, CBS, 1958 (Box 7)
    - Campbell, Patton, Wings of the Dove, Undated (Box 7)
    - Colt, Alvin
      - Fanny, three costume designs, Undated (Box 7)
      - Greenwillow, four costume designs, Undated (Box 7)
    - Conklin, John M.
      - The Balcony, Hartford Stage Co., 1966 (Box 7)
      - The Spy Who Came in From the Cold Place, Undated (Box 7)
    - Dancy, V., Othello Verdi (Box 7)
    - Darling, Robert, Aida, act 2, Undated (Box 7)
    - Elder, Eldon
      - Dear Brutus, 1958 (Box 8)
      - Morning Sun, Phoenix Theater, New York, 1963 (Box 8)
      - Shinbone Alley, 1957 (Box 8)
    - Gesek, Tadeusz, Dialogues of the Caramelites, acts 1 and 3 (Box 8)
    - Goheen, Douglas Scott, The Seventh Seal (Box 8)
    - H (full surname unknown)
      - Oh Dad, Poor Dad, costume designs, Undated (Box 8)
      - Commodore Roseabove, 1965 (Box 8)
      - Jonathan, scenes 1-3, Undated (Box 8)
      - Madam Rosepettle, scenes 1-3, Undated (Box 8)
      - Rosalie, scenes 2-3, Undated (Box 8)
    - Harris, James Berton, Othello, Desdemona, Yale Drama School, 1966 (Box 8)
    - Hastings, Russell, Taming of the Shrew, Undated (Box 9)
    - Helvenston, Harold, Peking Politics, Yale Drama School, 1927 (Box 9)
    - Hendrickson, George, Oh Dad, Poor Dad, Tulane, 1965 (Box 9)
    - Jacoby, Victor E.
      - The Dragon, Adelphi University Traveling Theater, 1954 (Box 9)
      - Ho_Dan_ Zo, Columbia, 1936 (Box 9)
      - Lilions, Adelphi University, Undated (Box 9)
      - Night of the Iguana, 1964 (Box 9)
    - Keene, Jay B.
      - Cradle Song, 1962 (Box 9)
      - Everyman, Stephen College, 1957 (Box 9)
      - Hedda Gabler, Undated (Box 9)
    - Kurdt, Raymond T., The Bays Between, State University College at New Paltz, 1965 (Box 9)
    - L (full surname unknown), The Spy Who Came in From the Cold Place, Undated (Box 9)
    - Leve, Samuel, Peer Gynt, Undated (Box 9)
    - Lowenstein, Henry, La Bohème, Undated (Box 9)
    - Mason, Richard
      - Antony and Cleopatra Emobarbus, 1963 (Box 9)
      - Don Juan, costume for Death Time, 1962 (Box 9)
      - Hamlet, costume for a soldier, 1963 (Box 9)
      - King Lear, two versions, 1965 (Box 9)
      - Oedipus at Colonus, Undated (Box 9)
    - May, Henry, Dr. Faustus, Belzebub, 1964 (Box 9)
    - Mitchell, Robert D., Harry, Moon and Night, American Place Theater, 1965 (Box 9)
    - Newton, James
      - A project, untitled, Undated (Box 9)
      - Tiny Alice, Undated (Box 9)
    - Odle, Dwight Richard, We're Off to the Moon, 1963 (Box 10)
    - Riggs, Otis, Nantucket, ballet, Undated (Box 10)
    - Rogers, James, Macbeth, Amherst College, Undated (Box 10)
    - Ross, John, High Cockalorum, acts 1 and 2, Yale Drama School, 1962 (Box 10)
    - Salzer, Beeb, Gounod's Romeo & Juliet, Manhattan School of Music, 1964 (Box 10)
    - Saxe, Stephen, Porgy and Bess, New York City Center, 1962 (Box 10)
    - Shaw, possibly Shay, Captain Brassbound's Conversion, acts 1 and 2, Undated (Box 10)
    - Shirley, Donald J.
      - "Advertising film", Undated (Box 10)
      - "Alka Seltzer," VPI film, Undated (Box 10)
      - "Don Giovanni," NBC TV, 1960 (Box 10)
      - "Mitch Miller Show", 1951 (Box 10)
      - "Rip Van Winkle", 1963 November (Box 10)
      - "Salem Cigarettes", Undated (Box 10)
      - "Sing Along", 1963 (Box 10)
    - Soule, Donald R., Long Day's Journey Into Night, Loeb Drama Center, 1966 April (Box 10)
    - Stevens, John Wright, Within the Gates, 1966 (Box 10)
    - Stover, Fred
      - Lakwe, ballet for ABC TV, Undated (Box 10)
      - Man and Superman, Undated (Box 10)
    - Whaley, Russell G.
      - Belle Lamar, Undated (Box 11)
      - Carmen, act 4, Undated (Box 11)
      - The Tempest, Ariel, Prospero, Undated (Box 11)
    - White, Newton, untitled, acts 1-4, Undated (Box 11)
    - Wilcox, Richard
      - The Madwoman of Chaillot, acts 1 and 2, Goodman Theater, 1964 (Box 12)
      - A project, untitled, Undated (Box 12)
      - Unidentified designer
        - Act 7, scene 2, Undated (Box 12)
        - Ground row, street scene, Undated (Box 12)
        - Infirmary in convent, Undated (Box 12)
        - Mr. Mississippi, Habima Theatre, 1960 (Box 12)
        - Sentry's post at gate, Undated (Box 12)
        - Twelfth Night, Undated (Box 12)
    - Williams, Henry B., In Good King Charles' Golden Days, two costumes, 1965 (Box 12)
    - Wills, Mary
      - Hans Christian Andersen, Undated (Box 12)
      - Up in Central Park, 1966 (Box 12)
      - A Project, Undated (Box 12)